Leah: Let’s look at how adults
and parents can help children and
young people make good lifestyle
choices to help with Self Esteem.
Rhiannon: If a child or young person
feels unimportant or worthless, it
will likely lead to sad emotions
and create poor self-esteem.
This is a common factor in children
and young people experimenting
with alcohol or drugs and other
destructive or risky behaviours.
Having strong self-esteem is essential
as a child or young person grows up, as
they will face many challenges and having
a healthy self-esteem is fundamental
in making safe and healthy choices.
a child or young person should be
shown lots of love and positivity and
told why they are special as a person.
Children and young people
remember the positive things
and they make them feel loved.
Leah: An adult or parent who shows
positivity, when faced with challenges
can implant that on a child or young
person and show them how to handle
themselves when they too are challenged.
They can also learn to not be afraid
to show opinions and ideas and it’s
ok to disagree sometimes as long as
They consider the opinions of others.
Rhiannon: All children and young people
need verbal discipline from time to time,
but if the criticism is directed at the
child as a person, rather than being
directed at their inappropriate behaviour
or actions, it can have a negative effect,
causing them to feel ridiculed or ashamed.
A parent should approach their role in
this aspect of their child’s development
by acting as a life coach or a teacher,
rather than a disciplinarian or punisher.
If a parent is unhappy with their
behaviour, they should tell them,
but make clear they still love them.
Leah: When an adult is commenting on,
or correcting the behaviour of a child
or young person, it is important that
they are fair and firm, as this will
help the child or young person to accept
responsibility for their bad behaviour.
All children need to accept
responsibility for their behaviour,
and learning self-discipline is a
very important part of growing up.
Rhiannon: Valuing effort over perfection
can encourage Children and young people
to take on new challenges and by not
being over-anxious about success,
they might try more activities and
set themselves more goals and plans
for things they’d like to accomplish.
Also getting praise for any improvements
or successes can help even more.
Leah: Children and young people need to be
guided to make good lifestyle changes for
the benefits of their mental well-being.
This could involve encouraging
them to discover and develop their
talents, through clubs, groups and
activities or to express themselves
creatively, through art, drama or music.
finding something they are good at can
provide a huge boost to their feelings
of self-worth and their self-esteem.